There is something really strange going
on with SpaceX.
And we got to talk about it because
yesterday SpaceX reported earnings.
Today, the stock tanked. And tomorrow,
there're going to be some really massive
stock lockups that
open up, which means potentially more
people will sell.
But, the real strange thing I want to
start with
actually looks like a little chart. And
it's not a stock price chart. Instead,
it has to do with
selling compute, which seems to be most
of what SpaceX really wants to spend
their money on right now. In fact, about
85%
of all of the money that they collect,
they're not burning it on rockets or V3
Starlink satellites to get that 10x
faster
well, Starlink.
No. It's going into data centers.
Yes, microhard and minihard.
But there's a little weird thing going
on, and I feel justified in asking some
questions.
Start with the chart.
Let's say on the left side of the chart,
you have annual revenue.
Okay? From your data centers. This will
be measured in megawatts
per
you know, month, let's say. So, we'll
call it MW
per month, okay? And this will be in
millions of dollars. So, put a little M
there. Let's say you make $4 million
per megawatt that you're able to sell of
compute, and the scale is zero
to 30.
And let's say you make four.
Well, that would put you somewhere over
here at the dotted line, right? Pretty
low, pretty close to the bottom. That's
understandable, right? Now, on the
x-axis, we're going to have the cost
per megawatt to build these facilities.
And this is going to be in millions of
dollars, and it's also going to go from
0 to 30.
In this case, let's say the average cost
for like an, you know, an Ebbias or
Corweave is something like $15 million
per megawatt.
Well, then you'd be somewhere in the
middle. So, we'd have this intersection
point somewhere over here, right? So,
the average data center should be
somewhere low and in the middle of this
chart.
Now, let's say you're a total freak of
nature. Let's think about this for a
moment. Total freak, and you blow all
your money on the best chips in the
world, and you literally pay the highest
premiums possible,
and you make average revenues. Well, in
that case, average revenues would be
down here in the chart, and you'd be
paying, you know, a premium, you'd be
over here to the right, all right? So,
this is average.
This right here would be paying a lot
and earning very little.
Now, let's say you were a different kind
of freak.
Let's say somehow
you were able to convince the world that
you could actually build data centers
for close to this side of the line,
cheaper than anybody else, yet somehow
you were able to make six times as much
money as all of the other people selling
the same stuff.
I mean, that'd be crazy, right?
In that case, though, you would be
somewhere over here on the chart, right?
That'd be crazy. So, if you overpay and
under earn, you're here.
If you're average, you're here.
And if you're
well,
crazy, I guess, or or magnificently
crazy, then you're up here in the chart.
Okay. So, why did we just go through
that exercise of where you might end up
sitting on the chart?
Well, what if I told you there was
something going on with SpaceX that puts
it in a very unique position on this
chart?
Uh what we would call a statistical
outlier.
Let's pull up a real chart.
Holy smokes.
So, we've got Correlate down here at a
normal, you know, cost to build per
megawatt. Nebia's over here at a normal
kind of cost to build per megawatt in
this middle range right here. And then
earnings are somewhere between, you
know, 2 million to 5 million dollars per
megawatt
uh per month, right? Well, actually in
this case it's annual. Whatever. Per
month per annual, you get the idea.
Okay.
SpaceX
actually shows up
right here
at the top earning six times its peers
and somehow building for 1/5 of its
peers. This is a statistical anomaly.
Let's look at the actual data here.
SpaceX is telling everyone that they can
build for 2.7 million dollars per
megawatt. Uh okay. And that their annual
revenue is somewhere around 30 million
dollars. Annual, I did say per month on
my little sample whiteboard, meant to
say annual.
Um
Nebia's
is able to collect revenue of about 4.5
million. Correlate is able to do about
1.65.
Core Scientific can do 1.75.
The average hyperscaler collects 2.3.
So, somehow SpaceX is out-earning all of
them.
And they're able to buy it all for
substantially less than everybody else.
So, that got me to be a little bit
curious. What's going on here? How could
this be possible? Is this an Elon
premium?
No.
Is this being an Elon hater?
Let's actually analyze what's going on.
See, in the earnings call, Elon Musk
suggested that they are able to install
compute with less than a 1-year cost
recovery, which seemed like an
incredible claim, so I wanted to stress
test it. And then I found out where this
2.7 million dollars per megawatt
actually came from.
It's not from an auditor. It's not from
an SEC filing. It's not in the S-1. It's
nowhere on a formal document. It's
simply what SpaceX has suggested they
were able to build the Colossus 2 data
center at, not including any GPU
hardware.
It's literally just the shell.
No audits, just a management opinion of
what it cost for them to put the shell
together and the power infrastructure.
So, is it a lie?
No.
But, it's missing a whole lot of
context. See, Deutsche Bank argues to
now fill this up with GPUs, you would
have to say that the cost per megawatt's
going to be somewhere between 25 to 30
million dollars, which is essentially in
line with the industry averages.
Huh, interesting. So, in that case,
what is Colossus 2?
Well, Colossus 2, and Colossus 1 for the
matter, are actually considered
brownfield data centers. A brownfield
data center is different from a
greenfield data center, and it has
nothing to do with green energy.
Brownfield data centers are basically
data centers that are built inside of an
existing structure, like an old
manufacturing facility that used to be
used for something else, that can now be
a data center. This is what SpaceX did
back when it was XAI for Colossus 1 and
2. They took over existing factories
with power shells in place, faster to
permit, even though Elon still ended up
using unpermitted gas turbines, and
SpaceX has had to promise to remove
those illegal gas turbines by July of
2027, so in about a year from now, so
the clock is ticking on that. That's a
very different
speed-wise and cost-wise
than taking a blank piece of land, going
through permitting for 18 months to 24
months uh compared to the 91 days
for slapping together Colossus 1 and 2,
which uh individually, the the faster
one, Colossus 2, was done in 91 days,
you have to admit, is pretty freaking
impressive.
But, when you hear that 2.7 million
dollars per megawatt, you have to know
that is a brownfield deployment, inside
of an existing facility with a lot of
power infrastructure and utilities
already in place. It is not building up
from the the dirt.
And it does not incorporate GPUs,
or the servers, or the switching
equipment, or the other things that
really make a data center tick.
Now, that's really important because the
marketing SpaceX investors, a lot of
them are using, is this 2.7 million
dollar per megawatt figure.
And it's going to screw up a whole lot
of estimates for people. So, that is
important.
Now, in fairness, that's just part one.
Because even if it costs you, say,
Deutsche Bank's estimate, take a
midpoint of like 27.5 million dollars
per megawatt to deploy, let's say, mini
hard or macro hard. Okay? Let's just say
you could pull that off.
If Anthropic is willing to pay
$30 million
per megawatt,
you know, per year, then Anthropic is
basically paying SpaceX back
the full investment in less than a year.
That could then still be defensible,
right? So, is that good? Does that mean
we're ready to rock? The chart didn't
mean anything?
Not quite. See, the problem with this
chart is that it has
two
concerning issues for SpaceX.
Number one is what we started with,
which is the marketing around cost to
build. How are we on the far left side?
Oh, got it. We're actually not on the
far left side. If we want to use
advanced hardware and actually consider
the GPUs, we're actually over here on
the far right side. But, the marketing
implies that they're over here on the
far left side. All right, misleading,
but hey, a little bit more research and
we can get that. But, there's a second
problem.
The second problem is how is SpaceX
possibly sitting at this much revenue
when everybody else is sitting so low on
revenue?
Well, to understand that, we have to
understand the incentives.
First, Colossus number one was rented to
Anthropic. The entire facility was.
Colossus number two was partly rented to
Anthropic.
And that's partly because SpaceX says
they're going to focus less on training
and more on inference, and then they
rented some to Anthropic at a premium
that we're just going to talk about in
just a moment. There were some rumors
that Grok was having latency issues,
and SpaceX wasn't actually able to
properly utilize these facilities for
training
Grok, but those are just rumors, so
we'll let that be. That was reported by
The Information, which is often
considered credible, but that rumor
never ended up getting verified or
denied. It just sort of died.
So, the revenue rates for the Anthropic
contract are $30 million per megawatt
per year. Still gives you the one-year
break-even. It's about a 10-month
break-even payback, right? Once you
consider all of the computing
infrastructure.
Google then signed a contract with
SpaceX for some of their extra compute
at $50 million per megawatt per year.
Which is really interesting because 50 /
30 is a 67%
premium to Anthropic. Google signed a
67% premium over Anthropic when
Anthropic is already paying a 6x premium
over what these market rates are from
hyperscalers, Core Scientific,
CoreWeave, or Nebius.
Now, why is that? Is it just because
they want it and and it's available at
SpaceX? Come and get it, but you're
going to have to pay a premium for it
and and you know, Elon's just really
good at negotiating?
Maybe.
Or
could it be this?
Google holds $94.1 billion in SpaceX
shares.
That was as of June 30th.
So, the valuation has certainly changed
a lot, but in Google's last earnings
report the vast majority of their
earnings came from appreciation in
SpaceX shares.
Of that $94.1 billion, $80 billion of
their money is locked up on the
short-term lockup schedule, $14.1
billion locked up on the long-term
schedule. So, a lot of lockups.
The bulk of Google's net income
in that quarter of their $114 billion
SpaceX appreciation.
In fact, this is the first quarter
Google went cash flow negative and
people are like, "Okay, this is an
anomaly." is how it was described.
But, regardless of Google's earnings,
this video isn't about Google's
earnings. We know that Google benefits
massively if SpaceX stock booms.
Well, Google also has a buddy renting
from SpaceX. You'll see why they're a
buddy in just a moment.
It's Anthropic. Colossus 1 is rented
from Anthropic.
Google happens to hold a $124 billion
stake in Anthropic, which is actually
almost 30% bigger than the stake they
hold in SpaceX itself.
So, let's put this together for a
moment. Google makes money if SpaceX
stock goes up.
Google overpaying for SpaceX stock on a
cancelable 3-year contract
could make SpaceX stock go up.
Google has a $15.3 billion backstop tied
to a data center for
we don't know who in Hubbard, Texas.
Well, who's [snorts] developing a data
center in Hubbard, Texas?
Anthropic.
Anthropic
might need some backstops.
Might also need some money.
Anthropic making money means they too
can overpay SpaceX
for SpaceX's Colossus,
which then boosts SpaceX's stock,
theoretically,
and
helps Google.
>> [laughter]
>> And if Google gets helped, and Anthropic
does well, then Google wins again
because Google owns a ton of Anthropic.
So, you got yourself a massive cluster
circle to explain this anomaly.
So, the marketing of $2.7 billion per
gigawatt excludes all the GPUs. The
reality is they're not building these
facilities cheaper, and even if they
could get the shell, like the 10% of the
cost cheaper, because they're using a
brownfield strategy to get speed going,
uh
when they actually try to scale this and
start going to greenfield, which is
taking a, you know, dirt lot of land and
turning it into facility, it's going to
take a whole lot longer.
That's problematic on the cost side. So,
the cost side is an illusion. You're
really over here at the hyperscaler
average. You are not unique on these
costs.
Jensen does not like you enough to
basically commit a massive proportion of
his GB200 chips
>> [laughter]
>> to you at a discount. It ain't
happening.
Uh and then these premium rates
actually, we don't know if this is true,
but up-
appear to be from people who would
substantially benefit from SpaceX stock
doing really well.
The problem with these agreements at
these elevated terms
is renewal.
Or worse, cancellation.
See, Anthropic rented 100% of Colossus 1
with a 90-day rolling cancellation
right, which means at any point they can
give their 90-day notice
and essentially be done.
There is a uh a a sort of an initial
waiting period. All of those initial
waiting periods end by the end of the
year.
Although, there's one that could end
even sooner. I'll talk about that in
just a moment. Google, uh well, and then
Anthropic is also renting, in addition
to renting 100% of Colossus 1 with
90-day rolling cancellation rights,
they're renting part of Colossus 2 with
90-day cancellation rights. Google is
also renting from, so those were were
Anthropic. Google is also renting from
SpaceX and they also have the 90-day
cancellation rights. So basically the
90-day cancellation rights are
everywhere.
After the introductory periods, 90-day
lease cancellation right.
The problem is Google can actually
cancel early if SpaceX can't deliver
functional access for Google's deal by
September 30th.
Which that's in 56 days.
Now a problem for this
is memory.
See, Elon doesn't want to lose that
contract cuz it's going to
hurt their stock, which hurts Google. So
Google might not cancel anyway.
But Elon's already kind of building the
force majeure narrative of well, we we
couldn't deliver because it's not our
fault.
How's he doing that? Well, right here.
Then I look at the rate at which logic
and memory is being produced.
And one was always considered a limiting
factor here. The limiting factor
currently is memory. The memory output
is increasing by about 20% per year.
Normally that would be fantastic. But if
demand is increasing 20% uh but demand
is not increasing 20% per year, it's
increasing 200% per year.
So in other words, yes, prices are going
up for RAM. We already know that.
They're up, you know, 4x year over year.
But this is also planting a little bit
of a seed here that he might not be able
to fulfill that Google contract. Maybe.
Maybe I'm reading into that too much.
All right? We can't get the memory.
But then it's also worth thinking about
this.
A lot of the CapEx that SpaceX is going
to spend
is going to go into, at least in micro
and mini hard. Elon just talked about
this on X. He said, "We're going to put
N in the inner scope. We're going to put
220,000 GB 300 Nvidia chips and 800 G
NICs." Okay, these are your InfiniBand
connectors. into these data centers.
Each rack holds 72 GB200s.
So, that means we need 3,056 racks per
facility.
Each of these racks runs about $10
million. The $10 million rack.
Damn, that's a hot rack. Literally, they
got to cool the crap out of it.
>> [laughter]
>> But anyway, that's $30 billion for
racks.
Damn.
That's big.
Uh and then of course, you got to spend
money on InfiniBand. That's going to run
you a billion and a half. You got to,
you know, get the facility up. That's
going to be 4 to 8 billion bucks. You
got to get storage. That's going to be
and I'm not talking about like, you
know, for toilet paper, like actual um
you know, electronic storage. So, that's
going to be another 1.5 billion bucks.
So, your ballpark per facility here is
going to be about $40 billion.
You're going to spend about $80 billion
for micro and uh macro or mini and macro
hard, which are really just puns on
Microsoft.
The problem with this is
the only way those are going to prove to
be a 1-year payback period is if Elon
can get these
wild rates on compute, which nobody else
is being charged
and nobody else is charging.
So,
while it's possible they could pull it
off,
based on this initial information that
I'm seeing here,
I don't even like looking at the Wall
Street speculation because a lot of the
suits, the Goldman Sachs, the Morgan
Stanleys, a lot of these folks
have to play nice with Elon, otherwise
they're not going to get invited to the
earnings call anymore. They're not going
to get invited to the events anymore.
It's how it is. It's how they play the
game. And Goldman has to to at the Elon
events. JP Morgan has to be at the Elon
events because they got a lot of
customers at the banks
that like Elon and want Elon
information. They want to feel like
their bankers are there for them. It's
endless marketing marketing. Every
single time they pick up that that call.
Oh, here's your analyst. What Here look,
you know?
Our next question comes from Edison Yu
with Deutsche Bank. Your line is open.
Marketing. Every freaking time.
Marketing. That's all it is.
So, I'm a little sus about what's going
on here with
uh SpaceX's AI rev.
And that's where we can actually get
into some of the earnings because you
could see here earnings did blow up in
AI. They blew up from 737 million to two
2.5 billion. A lot of that was due to a
1.6 billion dollar boost, which is a
very strange flat number, as we began to
offer cloud services to customers.
Okay. So, obviously it's a flat number
like this because it's probably
you know,
two one or two customers paying a flat
deposit. It's probably Anthropic and
Google paying some form of a deposit. We
don't know with certainty because they
don't give us any more clarity here.
Okay, great. So, we're boosting our
revenue here. We're obviously still
losing money over here
from AI. We're you know, I don't think
anybody's expecting SpaceX to be cash
flow uh or or a net income positive
tomorrow and they certainly are not. Uh
you know, over the last 6 months they've
burned almost 5 billion dollars here.
So, the net loss is is present. Their
negative cash flow here is about 25
billion dollars in the last 25 months.
And if we look at their balance sheet, I
will give them credit. They've done a
great job at the suckening.
In during the suckening where they
raised basically 85 billion dollars.
Plus then they came in and raised uh a
refinance facility afterwards or or you
know, a loan facility a loan ladder, I
guess I should say afterwards.
They've raised a lot of money.
So, here we can see $36 billion in debt,
$13 billion in bills, approximately
50-ish, right? And then they've got on
top like once I subtract that out of
these marketable securities and the cash
they've got here, they in fairness have
$50 of free cash.
That's probably good enough for the 6
months of CapEx. So, I'm going to assume
uh that uh will be spent in the next 6
to 9 months.
So, in the next 6 to 9 months, they will
have burned all of their free cash.
And that free cash is going to build
facilities that Elon is telling us have
fewer than a 1-year break-even economic
set
if you include cursor revenues.
But, when we actually analyze those
contracts, we're really suspicious that
those contracts are actually being made
because they really want this Colossus
compute or they're being made because
they're trying to pump the SpaceX stock,
which would make it a very dangerous
proposition to overbuild assuming you're
going to be able to rent out that
hardware those GB300s at those prices.
So, call me skeptical, but I think it's
a reasonable to be skeptical and and a
little bit nervous about this.
So,
I don't know what to make of these
projections of we're going to get to a
hundred billion dollars of annual
recurring revenue, eventually we're
going to get to a trillion dollars of
recurring revenue. To me, it's hard to
justify that
uh when you actually dive into some of
the initial notes that I made, which
we've already gone through. Contract the
contract termination rights, the
incentives for way overpaying compared
to what you're seeing with Nebius and
Coreweave. And keep in mind the business
that they're getting into. This is a an
extremely capex heavy business that
they're getting into and the vast
majority of it is
AI infrastructure. See? Look at that.
Second quarter we spent 18.4 billion
dollars of which 85.8%
is AI infrastructure. The vast majority
of it. Which means 14.2% of the money
that they're lighting on fire is
actually going to light money on fire
via rockets.
And I want them to light the money on
fire with rockets.
>> [laughter]
>> Instead they're throwing it into AI
infrastructure.
So I'm a little bit disappointed by that
because I think they're throwing a lot
of good money
after something that is potentially a
misleading good. Now, why would I call
it a misleading good?
Well, and this is not here to bag on
uh Nebius or Coreweave.
But let's just be real about the actual
numbers of those individual companies
and we can see, you know, one is doing a
little better than the other but both of
them have some issues. So let's go take
a look at this.
First Coreweave. Okay, so Coreweave has
a capital expenditure of about 7.7
billion dollars in just 3 months. Free
cash flow of negative 4.7 billion
dollars. We can actually see that right
here. All right? So there's our capex of
7.7. We subtract this, we're negative
4.7 billion dollars of free cash flow.
Net loss over here 740 million dollars.
So, you know, not great. They did
increase their receivables a lot though
the current estimates are that a lot of
those receivables are just from three
customers.
Potentially as much as
89% of Coreweave's receivables might be
Microsoft, OpenAI, and Google.
And it's not uncommon for those
companies to pay 15 to 25% up front and
then you actually get a smaller set of
receivable income over time.
The problem with CoreWeave though isn't
so much the cash flow statement. We know
they're burning the money on
reinvesting. It's actually their balance
sheet. Look at the balance sheet. Uh
I've got about 4.3
billion dollars as of March 31st of
capital here.
And I have bills to pay. I have
long-term debt of 17.3 billion. Okay,
that that already doesn't look good
because you know, I've got again 4.3
billion dollars and 17.3 of long-term
debt. I don't like that ratio at all.
But let's just pretend they had no
long-term debt for a moment. How much
short-term debt do they have which would
be their accrued payables, accrued
liabilities, their current debt, and
other current liabilities? If I just add
those categories up, we are sitting at
bills to pay of 15.1 billion dollars.
Which is two and a half times as much
cash that they actually have.
Now in fairness, I'm pretty sure they've
been raising money
since this last filing.
But that's the only way they could
survive is through issuance. They have
to issue debt and stock. That's the only
way they could raise or or or survive
rather. Like this is like this is not
they're not
in my opinion, it's not like they're
like, "Hey, we're going to go raise
money and we're going to go buy houses
at a 20% discount." They're going
"We need to raise money to survive."
>> [laughter]
>> Uh a little different.
In addition to that,
they are now having to raise at over a
10% yield on their debt.
The Wall Street Journal was reporting
that they were expecting to raise at
1.25% lower than that. They actually had
to raise it by 1.25% just to attract
enough capital so they could end up
getting uh what what they needed.
Huh.
Okay, not great.
Then, we can get into the Nebulous
numbers. So, the Coreweave numbers,
yeah, it leaves something to be desired.
Nebulous is not as bad. They're in a
much
I would call it They're in a
significantly better position in terms
of their balance sheet. They've got
about 9.3 billion dollars of cash, and
I've got current liabilities here of
about 1.3, and that includes like 700
million dollars of deferrals. They do
have 8.4 of long-term debt. So, you
know, there are some bills to pay in
that, but they've got enough money.
But, they are also spending a lot.
They're spending pretty much all of
their cash flow.
Uh spending 2.5 billion dollars. And of
course, they're also issuing notes,
warrants, whatever they can do to keep
raising
or taking investments from Nvidia, which
they did do that as well.
This is a very capital-intensive
business.
The issue that I have is why are
companies like Coreweave and Nebulous
having to basically give away their
compute relative to those contracts that
Google and Anthropic have with SpaceX?
And then, it always seems to point right
back to Google's ownership in Anthropic
and SpaceX.
It's all a big circle jerk.
Not good.
NOT GOOD AT ALL. I DON'T KNOW,
SOMETHING'S PRETTY WEIRD about that.
Now, if I go to the other portions of
the earnings call just to see if there's
anything else that's interesting. Yes, I
do think it is exciting to hear that
maybe we're going to have a launch
cadence for rockets that will get to at
least one flight per day.
It's worth noting that their cadence in
2025 was about one flight every other
day.
But,
you know, I'm I'm generally
am going to add multiple to Elon Musk's
time frames. So, if he says we're going
to get to one launch every day,
uh that might be years from now. Uh in
fairness, by the 2030s, there are
estimates that there are going to be
multiple launches per day, and you'll
end up having thousands of launches per
year.
The issue here is you have two types of
rockets. You have the Starship, which is
on test flight 14, will be the next one
after they, you know, crane the Starship
13 out of the ocean.
Um
you know, that's a that's a test
vehicle. Elon says they've uh you know,
they're they're optimistic about the
heat shielding technology they have,
which is great.
But, Falcon is no longer taking orders.
The Falcon rocket will be flown through
2029, and they're starting to turn away
business because they only want to do
Starship, which will take larger
payloads.
And Falcon's only going to do 70 flights
at an estimate of 2028. Well, I don't
think Starship's going to be ready by
then. And certainly not in in mass
flight production. This is why they're
already built, you know, they need four
launch pads built for this.
Um
and you know, these these plans are all
in works, but uh in the works, but uh
usually these things take a whole lot
longer. And uh I think a lot,
unfortunately, of their CapEx isn't
actually going
to the Starship or launch side of the
business.
As we saw, it's going to AI. And I'm
skeptical that that is a great
investment. I think that's obvious, and
I think there are reasons for that. It
did not sink, by the way. It is being
towed right now. So, let's delete that.
The uh Starship 13.
I do think it's cool that they're going
to release V3 satellites for Starlink,
which is supposed to make the service
10x faster. Which is uh it's already
really fast. So, that's pretty
impressive. So, I'm not sure exactly by
what levels they're counting that. But,
um this is this is sort of my overview
of how I feel about SpaceX. Now, when
SpaceX first IPO'd, before it IPO'd, we
called for maybe a 30% run-up
and then a bleed-out. And so far, that's
exactly what we've had.
This tripling down on AI compute makes
the stock even more risky for me, given
that I don't have good visibility into
what realistic contract rates are.
And I honestly think we're being misled.
Thanks so much for watching, folks. If
you like my information, join us over at
meetkevin.com. Pay once to get lifetime
access to the trade alerts, buying,
selling, fundamental analysis, you name
it. The course is on building wealth.
Some [music] say you could write it off
on your taxes, and we'll see you in the
next one. Goodbye and good luck.
>> Why not advertise these things that you
told us here? I feel like nobody else
knows about this.
>> We'll We'll try a little advertising and
see how it goes.
>> Congratulations, man. You have done so
much. People love you. People look up to
you.
>> Kevin Paffrath, a financial analyst and
YouTuber, Meet Kevin. Always great to
get your take.